Esse Forrester O'Brien papers, Inclusive: 1933-1937, undated, Bulk: 1934-1935, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Esse Forrester O'Brien papers
Inclusive: 1933-1937, undated, Bulk: 1934-1935, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1799
O'Brien, Esse Forrester, 1894 - 1975
6 document boxes
A collection of documents pertaining to the creation of the book Art and Artists of Texas, one of the earliest systematic attempts to catalogue artists in the state of Texas.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Esse Forrester O'Brien was born in Waco, Texas, on 1894 November 21. She attended Waco High School and earned a fine arts diploma in 1913 from Baylor University. O’Brien completed a year of postgraduate work in art at Baylor and studied under George Bridgman at the Art Students League in New York City. She continued to study art and writing until she returned to Waco and earned a B.A. from Baylor in 1934. Esse Forrester married John L. O’Brien in 1917. She published Art and Artists of Texas in 1935. O’Brien died 1975 May 21 in Waco.
Scope and Content
This collection contains papers and materials gathered and written during the years of 1933 through 1937. They were all given to, gathered by, or created by Esse Forrester O’Brien in her attempt to make the book Art and Artists of Texas. The General Correspondence series is the largest (3 boxes) and contains papers mostly consisting of letters and their envelopes O’Brien received from artists, or people in the art field. These also include post cards, a photograph, newspaper clippings and pamphlets. The General Notes series contains O’Brien’s notes pertaining to the creation of her book, these are in both bound form (journals) and loose form (scraps of paper). The Biographical Sketch Notes series contains her groupings of notes directly related to biographical sketches of artists. These are all loose papers that she had bound together concerning art styles, artist’s names, as well as a rough draft and some other notes. The final series is Research Materials. This series contains pamphlets, booklets, images, and newspaper clippings all pertaining to art and artists in Texas. The newspaper clippings stored here are a representative sample of what she collected.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid, the correspondence was organized chronologically, while most of the notes and research materials were mixed together. Biographical sketch materials were all together. All materials were in folders with some titles, but no date ranges were available. A previous inventory was available but did not offer much detail. This previous arrangement was kept.
The collection is now organized into series: General Correspondence, General Notes, Biographical Sketch Notes, and Research Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1799. Acquired 1978-05-00
Related Resources
Related references
Barns, Florence Elberta. "O'Brien, Esse Forrester." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2016 April 16.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
O'Brien, Esse Forrester -- Correspondence.; O'Brien, Esse Forrester. Art and artists of Texas.
Subjects
Art -- Texas -- Sources.; Art -- Texas.; Artists -- Texas -- Sources.; Artists -- Texas.
Genres
Booklets.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Manuscripts.
- Correspondence, 1933-1937; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Unknown.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence with various people as O'Brien gathered information for her book Art and Artists of Texas.
  - Letters, 1933 January-October (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1933 November (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1933 December 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1933 December 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1934 January 1-5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1934 January 6-10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1934 January 11-16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1934 January 17-25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1934 January 26-31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1934 February 1-6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1934 February 7-12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1934 February 13-25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1934 March (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1934 April (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1934 May (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1934 June-July (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1934 August (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1934 September 1-20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1934 September 21-31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1934 October 1-8 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1934 October 9-15 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1934 October 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1934 November 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1934 November 11-16 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1934 November 17-30 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1934 December 1-11 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1934 December 12-30 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1935 January 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1935 January 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1935 February 1-12 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1935 February 13-21 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1935 February 22-27 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1935 March 1-11 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1935 March 12-21 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1935 April (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1935 May 1-19 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1935 May 20-November (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letters, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Manuscript Notes, undated; 2
  This series contains notes used by O'Brien as she wrote her book, including lists of people to contact and exhibits to see. This series is in average condition.
  - Notes (1 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes (2 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notes (3 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Notes (4 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notes (5 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bound Notes (1 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bound Notes (2 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Biographical Sketch Notes, circa 1934, undated; 3
  This series contains manuscript materials used for O'Brien's book Art and Artists of Texas. This series is in average condition.
  - Rough Draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Essays and Clippings, circa 1934 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Artists A-C, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Artists D-G, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Artists H-K, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Artists L-M, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Artists N-R, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Artists S-T, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Artists U-W, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Art in the Capitol Building, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Print Makers and Crafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cartoonists and Architects, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Iron Work, Odd Arts, and Wood Carvers, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Miniature Painters and Sculptors, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Monuments, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Fashion and Other Artists, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Loose Papers, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Research Materials, 1926-1935, undated; 4
  This series contains pamphlets, brochures, and other print materials used by O'Brien to write her book. This series is in average condition.
  - Booklets, 1928-1933 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Booklets, circa 1931 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Booklets, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Dallas Museum of Fine Arts Exhibition of Paintings, Sculptures, and Graphic Arts, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Booklets, 1931-1933 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Annuary, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Loose Papers, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1931-1935 (Box 6, Folder 9)